welcome to thinking ahead
about your legacy. I'm Dean Gregoire.
I think most of you I know.
So thank you for being here today.
I'm the director
and founder of the Electronic Literature
Lab here at Washington State University
in the Vancouver campus,
which is north of Portland, not in Canada.
And my lab is active
with a lot of different activities.
Many of you know that
we've been doing a lot of curation work.
The works on screen is our exhibition here
at the conference.
Last year
we did the conference Toronto conference.
We also have built
and maintained the next,
which is a lot of where
archival materials located.
Some of you are familiar with that site.
We also pioneered
the metadata schema called Elms,
which is being used for the conference
and for iOS five.
So you've seen that that were before.
And also we do the traversals.
And Stuart multiple
and I pioneered the traversal process
which is being used for archiving
and for even the LC five and four.
So anyway, I'm going to be talking today
about our work with born digital
archiving and preservation.
So that's what
we're going to be doing today.
So the workshop schedule is very simple.
There's four sections legacy which is why
you should save your work archives.
What should you save?
Archival practices.
How do I save it. And repositories?
Where do I save it?
Leading the workshop with me
or Holly Slocum and Holly
is a senior designer
and project manager of the Literature Lab.
Greg Philbrook is our lab's tech guru,
Ruth Woodcock
is our metadata specialist, and James
parents are born digital preservationist.
We have quite a few other people
in the lab that works with us,
but this is the team
that's speaking today.
Okay.
So I'm going to start with the case study
that illustrates
the need to think ahead about your legacy
when creating your projects.
And the one I've selected is Dinosaur
Lottery's Glide Project.
And some of you that have been around
a while might remember this project.
She published it in 1999,
in writing The Meridian,
but it was featured in ellos 2002
city of the Art Symposium cabaret.
It was showcased internationally
at festivals and conferences
through the mid 2000.
It's an incredibly beautiful piece.
It's a work of works, a system of systems,
to quote Diana directly.
It's expressed through nine sections
and you can see this database.
I mean, this interface here
that includes story labyrinth,
collaborative music,
obsession, lexicon, visual language,
architecture, resonant resonance,
just a beautiful piece
that embodies a lot of different things.
But driving the project is the question
that Diana was asking herself.
What does it mean
to move through a maze of language?
One of the components is the maze game.
This is a story world
fleshed out in her novel by the same name.
It features four young death dancers
from the social class called glide,
who perform a perform on a maze
for an audience of immortals.
The psychedelic nature of the language
and the story is tied to the origins
of the glide language,
and it's taught to workers by the lilies,
whose pollen causes hallucinations.
These workers are also called glide.
The gestures made when harvesting
the pollen resulted in the glide.
Language expresses glyphs.
And I'm going to show you
what I mean by this.
This is one of the screen captures I have
of this particular process in the work.
Okay.
The center where Diana worked
and which funded the project closed
and the server hosting it was shut down.
The only component
she had the rights to continue
were the narrative and the Oracle.
She published the Oracle
as an Apple app in 2012,
but it has not been maintained since 2017,
though
she managed to get it updated
four days before Apple shifted from the 32
bit OS support to the 64 bit,
so it's still somewhat accessible.
She had planned to do a trilogy
out of the book,
but her life took her
in a different direction.
Slater and I met at Kate Hills
2001 Summer seminar,
and continued our friendship while she was
working on her postdoc, and I was
while I was working in my postdoc,
and she was doing her PhD
at the University of Plymouth
in the UK under Roy Ascott.
I maintain notes, files, images,
videos, articles.
She wrote criticism about the work
during those years, starting 2001
to the present. Right.
So I've been holding on to all this
material myself.
A version of glide
was included in Hale's archive,
which was donated to the next,
which I was delighted to see.
It was one that was produced
for the IEEE conference as a demo.
You can also find on the website
her website on the Wayback Machine.
But when you
click to get into the glide project,
nothing works because it was built in.
Director.
The work is dead right,
and it's going to be hard
to even do a complete traversal of it.
But the materials I've managed to save
and my for my mean before I even became
an archivist and gather makes it possible
for me to tell you it's story, right?
I can tell you about glide
because I have the materials.
Quite a few of the materials.
My question to all of you for this
workshop is what are you leaving?
Are you leaving enough behind
to tell the story of your own work?
Right.
To make it possible for someone else,
even to tell the story if you don't.
So that's what
we're going to be talking about today.
And that's my introduction to the
workshop.
Let me scape here and go back
and turn this over to Holly.
Thanks so much, Deanie.
Hi everybody. Is Deanie mentioned?
My name is Holly Slocum.
I am thrilled to be here with you
all today.
So now that you know.
Okay, I want to save something.
What the heck should you save?
So note that
what I'm going to be talking about
is not an exhaustive list by any means,
but is going to help give you a starting
point to start thinking about the breadth
and the type of things that you'll
want to be saving around your work.
So as a case study, we're going to be
taking a look at one of the boxes
donated to the next by Richard Holton,
who's the author of Figures
at Fenton on Acid that was published
in 2001 by Eastgate Systems, Inc..
Denny is going to be holding
some things up for me
as I talk through some of these options.
So one of the first things
you want to think about
as you are developing a piece of work
that you're putting out into the world, is
what is the canonical copy of this work?
And by canonical copy
we mean the authorial copy
or the copy that you is the artist,
the as the major iteration
that you want people
to remember to distribute
and to access in the future.
So maybe you
you submitted initially to a journal,
but then you caught a bunch of bugs
and then you fix them,
and that's the version you want out there.
So having an idea of what that version is
can be really useful.
In Richard Holden's example,
he initially envisioned his work as a
a textual narrative that was published
in a literary journal called grain,
which Dean is showing you right here.
That evolved then,
as he was working on his MFA
into a digital hypertext narrative.
So he has held on to those early copies.
You can see the text there that Dean
is showing you in the original journal,
as he was self-publishing on CD-ROMs.
Right.
So he had these self-published CD ROMs
where he was putting early versions up.
Then he finally had what he sees
as the canonical copy
published by Eastgate Systems.
And so now that he kind of knows
that we're able to define
which one he says
is the authorial version.
Speaking of versions, though,
you want to save those old versions
as Richard Holton did.
He has that text narrative.
He has these early beta copies
that he was distributing at conferences
into his his professors at the time
and his dissertation committees.
So holding on to those you can see, there
we go, Dean, showing some of those
early versions, and we'll talk later
about how we define versions the next.
So you can have an idea about that too.
Keeping on
to these helps tell the story of how
the narrative traveled, how it changed,
and how the technology was driving
the story as well.
Companion material also.
So if you have anything that accompanies
your artwork like physical media
such as maybe a zine or a book,
or promotional materials
like posters, announcement cards,
those are really important to save too,
because they tell the story
not just of your work,
but also of the field
and what was happening in the field.
Denise holding up examples of Richard
Holden's notes.
These are the notes that he was taking
as he was figuring out
what the hyper textual structure of this
piece was going to look like,
how the lexia were going to lay it out,
be laid out where the links were.
This is a work
that's really connected to its structure
and the number of links,
and where those are going
and how they connect to each other.
We're incredibly important.
So having that documentation
actually became incredibly critical
when preserving, reconstructing
and trying to keep that work accessible
for future generations, because we knew
what the artist had made decisions by
so we could inform that
in preservation processes.
We also found that contracts have been
incredibly useful documents to hold on to,
not just to protect yourself.
Of course, and to say, hey,
I did do this thing, but also helps us
negotiate metadata errors like date
collaborators or publication details
that maybe have gotten lost in time
or were misprinted or miss distributed.
The big takeaway here
is that the archives that you save
and what you save tell your story.
It is our human nature
to fill a void of information
with speculation, and with what
information and knowledge we can find.
So keeping
your archives gives you an opportunity
to have a voice in
how that story is constructed.
Just like Deanie was able to
then reconstruct what is left of glide
through what exists from it.
You know you can do the same thing
by leaving these breadcrumb trails
through a multi multi-media
approach of documentation.
I want to mention that
ChatGPT and Claude
and a lot of the AI systems
that we're talking about in
this conference are very useful,
but the information that they have
is not necessarily correct.
And I find myself constantly
correcting these AI systems and feeding it
to the data I have so that it does
have the correct publication dates.
It misappropriated a work,
but to another artist, I had to fix that.
So a lot of things like that, doing that
kind of hands on training of these systems
that then go out and distribute
information, that's incorrect.
Just making
sure that's not happening. Right.
And so having this data, I was at the cell
project discussion earlier.
And so the dates for, for example,
Michael Joyce's afternoon
story are very diverse.
And that's because there's,
as I say, a thousand times, 18 editions
and 15 versions.
The canonical version is not the one
that's listed and most of the places
you look.
So training systems to,
to be able to get to that data and making
sure the data that we have in
the next is correct,
we're going to get to that
in a little bit.
We're going to shift now
to archival practices.
How do I save it.
And Holly's going to kick it off
with documenting processes.
Yeah.
So this this ties in really nicely
into what
we were just talking about,
which is you know, what do you save.
Because a lot of those things, you know,
are deeply connected to your process.
So first, it's important to emphasize
that we as the archivists
and preservationists of the next,
take the stance that we do not want
a preservation or archival process
to just prescribe how you make your art,
make your art, how and where
and why you want to make it.
If you want to make your art on a platform
that is dead
or is going to die,
that's part of the piece in itself.
Don't stop doing that.
You don't make it however you want,
but also consider
documenting its existence.
And there are a lot of ways
that you can do that.
A lot of electronic literature also isn't
web based, even though much of it is.
A lot of us make installations
that are digital pieces.
A lot of us do performances
that are fleeting.
Net proms and platforms die.
So documenting what's happening around
that lets us know that it's still existed
without being constrained
by the preservation process
of only creating open source software,
you know?
So some stable documentation formats
that we have found
come up over and over again
in the Electronic Literature Lab over
our 15 years of doing
this work, is printed
materials, of course, and not just printed
materials, but printed materials
that somebody printed out, organized,
and intentionally held on to.
We had printed emails from ELO
and Richard Holton
and Dena Larson that have helped us
identify and solve mysteries.
And those emails are gone digitally,
and had they not printed those out,
they would be.
That information would be lost.
So often that can be a stable way
of keeping information,
photographs, whether those are printed
physical photographs or JPEGs or gifts
or even bitmap images, have have lasted
quite a long time, are always a
wonderful way of documenting.
Video
has also been a really stable format.
You can see that even in, you know,
physical video formats from the early 90s
and 80 have been able to be digitized
and able to lacked many, many years
in ways that other formats have not.
And then, of course,
any open source
or agnostic kind of digital format.
So text files, PDFs, things like that
that don't require
specific proprietary software to view.
Those have also been things
that have lasted
so far in our experiences.
So I want to use a case study of Eric
Lawyers Artist website.
As I talk through
a couple of the last things to consider
when you are making documentation.
Eric is an incredible artist
that we have collected in the next.
He was one of the founding editor
of the journal vectors,
and he's also a wonderful digital
artist himself.
So here on his website
you can see many of his works.
And if we click into just the first one
here, you can already see
that he has wonderful documentation
about his work.
We always love when we have to archive
Eric's works, because he does
such a good job of saving information.
So you can see the title.
He has a short description,
he has the year, he includes the format,
and then we'll have these video
playthroughs or traversals.
And Dean and Stuart
have documented a more in-depth process,
and you can see that
here as well as photographs.
You can also
see if we go straight into his works,
we go down to his nonfiction,
and we look at a work like Public Secrets.
Again, wonderful video here
documenting what it looked like
in its interactivity description,
a video traversal,
another introduction video,
and then, of course, screenshots
as well as metadata.
One of the big things that he includes
here is his collaborator Sharon Daniel,
who actually did the design
and a lot of the writing,
and Eric was responsible
for the programing.
So having that collaboration information
is incredibly useful.
And not just that they both did it,
but their roles in it.
Right?
That Sharon was designing
and Eric was programing
helps us identify that in the future.
He even has recognition here as well.
This is especially useful
because Public Secrets is a work
that is no longer functioning.
It was created in flash and cannot
currently be restored with flash
preservation tools because of it
also complex database structure.
So this is one of the only things
we have left of the documentation, right?
We do have the files for this work,
so hopefully we'll be able to restore it
someday.
But these are the pieces that are left
right now that currently tell its story.
So as you wrap this up,
if you only take or as I wrap this up,
if you only take one thing away
from documenting your process,
I want you to take a multi-pronged
approach.
Don't just use photographs.
Don't just use videos. Right?
When we have this breadth of things
that describe
something
that gives us a much more robust picture,
this its existence,
as you can see in the example of slide.
So I will now go ahead and pass it
back off to DNA for the next section
of how we're saving things.
Yeah.
And I want to mention there's a difference
between a playthrough and a traversal.
Right.
So a place that was just simply doing
just kind of running the work, right?
Running through the work
and having a video recording of it.
A traversal is a very formal process
that Stuart and I developed back in 2013.
So quite a while ago,
in which the artist and readers
worked through the work together
on the original hardware,
using the original software
as close as possible so that we can get
the experience of the work
in this original glory.
Right.
And so we do a lot of traversals in here.
We've done it with Richard and John McDaid
and who else?
Other people at the conference.
Certainly we do a lot of playthroughs too,
so that's the difference.
The other thing I want you to think about,
and we've got The Odyssey's, a new movie
that's come out
right, old work, 3000 years old.
I'm an Odyssey scholar, by the way.
That was my background.
And so, you know, the thing that I keep
saying to people like a broken record
is that I know there were more than just
three epics produced 3000 years ago.
We know this,
but we have three left, and that's all.
And so my the impetus driving
so much of what
we're doing in the lab is,
I don't want your stuff to die.
I don't want someone in 3000 years to say,
oh, there's only one work.
And that was happening in a story.
Oh, wait a minute.
We got Shirley Jackson's Patrick girl,
and nothing else survives.
Nothing on the web survives.
We've already lost
a third of the web content.
If so much is going away
and we're holding on to it
because we want someone to know,
even in ten years that you existed
and the work you did was valuable
and spoke to a time that was important.
Right?
So that's my
my pitch to all of you to think about.
We're going to turn our attention
now to additions and versions.
Do you have questions? Anybody.
Before I go on to this next section.
Okay.
Let me do a little screen share with you.
I'll do the whole desktop.
This time we're going to look at.
So we're doing a lot of traversals
in these rebooting books.
This followed
after the Pathfinders project.
This is going to go here to volume three
to Stuart.
There we go.
We're going to go to Victor Garden.
So in every one of the books
that we're doing these open source
books, the thing that we've been doing in
the lab is versioning and additions.
Everything. Right.
And so we have the works
in our possession.
They're located in my personal collection
as well as the next, and we sit down
and go through them
and build out the versions and additions.
And so looking at this,
we've got five versions
of the different victory gardens.
If I scroll down and I go here to photos,
this section tells us what they look like.
So in this particular one, the first,
the first version of Victory Garden
that was published
is this green vinyl one, right?
We've taken pretty serious pictures of it
and giving a detailed discussion
about what's written on it
and what's what it says.
Right. Here's a floppy disks.
So if you wanted to study this,
you would then just click on it,
look at it,
and you can see even the scrapes
and tears of the paper,
which I think is important to think about.
We've done this for every one of the
additions and we've been doing this now.
I think we've done 30 of the 48 hypertext
published by Eastgate Systems, Inc.
and that's this, this this project. Right.
So it's important that people know this.
And I mentioned this this morning.
Let me share.
Now, I was mentioned today
in the cell project discussion
that recently there was a
I go on to eBay to buy floppy disk.
Right. Because I want to continue
buying as many as possible.
And there was a floppy disk for sale
for Michael Joyce's afternoon.
I was a CD rom for Michael Joyce's
Afternoon Story, and they were selling it
for some of my $350,
and I got seven of them in my collection
thinking, wow, this is great.
So I contacted this guy
and I said, so which version is this?
And he said,
I have no idea what you're talking about.
And folks, I'm going to say,
if you don't know the versions
of the things that you're looking at,
you know,
I could have naively bought that thinking
I had the ability to read after a story
on a computer with a floppy,
with a CD-ROM drive, and once I put it
in, if I have the wrong,
the wrong computer,
that would not read because it's a 2001
version and a 2007 version.
So knowing versions is really important
and making it easy for your readers,
future readers, to know what version
it is, is even more important.
By by definition, versions
mean that anytime your code is changed,
it's a new version.
So if your work is touched by code,
if you've changed the code,
you get a new version.
If you change words but not the code,
you only have a new addition, right?
So that's why we have 18 editions and 15
versions of Joyce's afternoon the story.
So we go through painstakingly doing this
with the early hypertext works
because those are the most fragile.
Write that in the flash and the director
and all these things
that we're working with.
So that is a little bit
about versions and additions.
I think James is going to talk now
about Alan Bigelow's This is Not a poem.
Thanks, Dini.
Thank you Holly.
So yeah, I've got a couple of examples
of some of that versioning taking place.
And as we know, especially with web works
and the two examples
I'll be showing our web works,
there is a lot of movement
with the code bases themselves
and programing languages evolve
and eventually things become deprecated.
So we come across this often in the lab.
And so we will make interventions
to restore functionality for those works.
But this, like Dini just mentioned,
constitutes a new version of that work.
So in the case.
So here let me
let me share my screen here.
We go.
Okay.
So the
first example that I want this victory
that I want to show is
this is not a poem by Alan Bigelow.
And this is a case
where the work had a flash
detection script
that was now no longer necessary
in the work also uses flash.
So as we know, flash is now deprecated.
So what we'll do,
and this is a lot of the work
that I do, is going in and sort of
turning off that flash detection script
and how I go about this,
I found that it's helpful
to have, in the actual version,
a sort of log of what has been changed.
So the rest of this file is
is original code that's still functional,
but I've marked clearly where, okay,
where does this script fail?
This is the particular block of code
that is now deprecated.
So we have a clearly marked.
And also where we've added updated code
that is functional.
And then we include our ending note there
to say okay we're done making edits here.
And then at the bottom
for our flash works,
we're now transitioning over to ruffle.
We just have to add a little ruffle
script here at the end.
And then this little snippet
is to turn off that big,
big ruffle player button.
So we figured out
how we can customize that.
But these changes would create a new
version of the work for modern browsers.
And I have one more quick
example which is going to be
poem by numbers.
And this is a case of just a JavaScript
update, so similar to the last one.
But for this instance
we had specific lines of code
that were deprecated.
So in this case it was documented at all.
So in the comment block
we include the problem area.
And what was the solution to the problem.
And again just like in the last example
we have our original code
block clearly marked
and the updated code block.
And now these can be on a wide
range of complexity or focus.
So we see a lot of different cases.
A lot of times it's just a
you know a selector
has been deprecated
and we're updating the selector.
But but yeah we this is how we go
about marking in the versions themselves.
What has been changed.
And you could do this like with a changes
file like a diff generated file.
But I think it's more explicit
to say okay, here's what broke, here's
what fixed.
And it just makes it easy
to know where to look in the file.
And yeah, so that is the example I have.
So I will go ahead
and hand it back to Dini.
So thank you James.
One thing I'll mention
is that there's restoration work
and there's reconstruction work.
And the lab does both.
And so we are pioneering
born digital reconstruction or what
I call conservation.
And so restoration example would be,
you know, something was produced
with an old file format which Greg
is going to talk about in just a second.
We changed out the format and we add
we update the format, right.
So it's accessible on new browsers.
On on contemporary browsers,
a reconstruction is when the entire work
doesn't function anymore.
And so with permission of the artist
and sometimes
the publisher
will totally reconstruct the work.
And I think one that you are about to show
James is Victory Garden.
So we did do a complete reconstruction
of that one.
We reconstruction
John the date, uncle, uncle buddy,
son house, Richard Holton for Gursky.
We've done something like ten different
reconstructions.
We're getting ready
to do Socrates in the in the
Labyrinth
this coming fall with David Kolb.
So we're excited about that one.
So reconstructing means doing the take
the whole thing out of story space
or HyperCard or Hyper Gate and make it
available in open source languages.
And know that when Stuart and I
were working on Pathfinders,
we painstakingly
look to see what formats were
more durable.
I guess is the best word to say.
None of them are going to last forever,
but which ones are more durable today?
And we found that video and open
source languages was the way to go.
And that's the way the lab has been
proceeding, even with our VR work.
And now I'm going to turn this over
to Greg, who's going to talk
about fall structure.
Excuse me, talk about file
structure and naming conventions.
All right. Hello.
Thank you.
Deanie, as you said,
my name is Greg Philbrook,
and I want to speak briefly about file
structure and naming conventions,
conventions, but specifically
from an archival perspective,
because obviously, as human beings,
we all have different ways
of organizing,
both physically and digitally.
And what makes sense to one person
may not make sense to another.
We're all individuals, right?
And I want to echo what we've already said
a couple of times that you should work
through your creative process
in whatever way you want.
This is not to say this is the proper way,
this is the improper way or anything
like that.
However, if you do wish to prepare your
digital works or collections or projects
or whatever you want to have handed off
to an organization or to an archivist,
it's a good idea to implement
some form of organizational structure
that will transcend your own understanding
and make it easier for whoever receives
your media objects to categorize
and archive them.
Luckily for us, many environments
in which we create in
have kind of seen an evolution
of standards over the years,
and these standards kind of provide us
with naming conventions and structures
and things that help pass on knowledge
and understanding from one person to
the next.
Just like
people, every project is different
and the best practices change depending
on the environment that you're working in.
Like if you work in a game
engine like Unity or Unreal, for example,
you know that there are many,
many project files
which are automatically generated
as you produce your scenes, right?
Pretty much you're going
to leave those alone for the most part.
And so your organizational method is less
kind of constrained
to the framework
that Unity or Unreal have decided for you.
But if you're creating video works inside
of Adobe Premiere, something like that.
I wouldn't suggest
that you try and organize the same way
that either of those game engines
do, right?
Nor should you try and structure
a web based project in the same way
that you would a soundscape project.
So for this particular example,
I just want to dip our toes
into a single environment
while still putting out that caveat.
That organization changes
depending on the person in the project.
But I want to dip into web based projects,
and the case study that I want to take
a look at in particular is the Electronic
Literature Collection, volume two.
I really like this example
because it has several layers to it
for us to look at, right?
Both kind of
very briefly like the editor's level,
but also at the individual artists level.
So let's go ahead and take a look.
I'm going to share my screen here.
All right.
Boom. Okay.
So this is the ELC volume two.
Glorious.
If you haven't gone through it
go through it.
But if I was handed
this like as an archivist
and I was given this project
and I wanted to take a look at it,
I would boot it up first thing
foremost, right?
I would view it from the user's end.
I'd go through,
click on any particular links.
What's nice is
we have a landing page up front,
and then we've got a landing page here.
And if I were to actually get in here,
you can see that
oh my god, clicked on the wrong one.
We would actually find ourselves
inside of the work itself.
So it's a fantastic little like interface
that we have going on here right.
But there's this is the editor level,
not actually at the artist level.
If we were to take a look
and see on the file side, we've got
just like we have here,
we've got our landing page index.
But then inside of the works
you'll see that the file structure
kind of echoes what we see
inside of the actual collection itself.
Right.
All of these are kind of siloed
into the individual works,
but organized by artists.
So we can easily kind of peruse
through here and see like, okay,
I understand this.
Like again,
from the perspective of an archivist
who may or may not have ever seen
this particular archive before.
So if I were to hop into one of these,
these are the individual artist works.
And inside of here
we've got very different
organizational structures, right?
If I were to hop into a different work,
you would see that
things are organized
very differently. Right.
Depending on the work that's in there.
But at least they are siloed
into the individual workspaces,
which already makes our job so much easier
to have it organized in a way
that is very straightforward and mirrors
the structure of the site itself.
When we pop in here, you can see that
there are subdirectories such as images.
Or if I go further down,
you can see that we have styles or videos.
We've got more unique ones like this city
between us and things like that.
But so we have subdirectories
that when we take a look inside of there,
like if I look inside of styles
as a web developer, styles
is typically where you put your styles.
So you find CSS files right inside of,
say, videos.
I expect to find videos and look at that,
I find videos.
So because these file names are very,
I would argue for the most part
very straightforward.
There are some that I would have to be
more familiar with the work to understand.
Like I might not know what backstopped
is immediately,
but having gone through the work,
I may have found a page called Back
Step or something like that, right?
That that the names help communicate
the content that is inside of them.
Right?
There's a lot of good things going on here
with the sorting in this organization.
Like I said, everything's kind
of organized into those subdirectories.
Everything's very legible.
The images are where they should be,
the videos are where they should be.
And I say should be with quotes,
as in like web standards.
But, you know, I could also say that
there are a few notes that we could make
here. Right?
Typical web standard formats
don't don't say to use underscores.
It says to use hyphens.
There are a couple of images
that I found in here
that may suddenly go into camel casing
instead of having everything lowercase.
You know,
they're a little things like that, right?
That sensibilities have changed over time.
Standards have changed over time.
And what makes sense to an archivist
or a web coder in 2026
might not have made sense in 2011
when the ELC two came out.
Or, you know, 2005 or 1998
or whenever a piece was made.
But what's important is that
this is so much easier to understand
for somebody
that this media object is handed off to,
than if it was all just kind of jumbled
all together
and put at the root of the directory,
right?
Whether those web standards
have changed over time,
or if just, you know, somebody
who's not a web developer hops in here,
what's really important
is that you are consistent.
You are clear with your file
naming structures.
Things go where they're supposed to.
You should always think to yourself,
not just how does this make sense
to organize for me, but for somebody
who has never seen this before?
How on earth would they view this?
How would they understand this?
And if you ask those questions
as you're building out your project,
I think you'll create something
that is a lot more readable
and consistent for people
and specially archivists when they're
going through to understand your piece.
So the takeaways that I want to give
are be consistent
with the organizational structure,
use the standards whenever you can
to help preserve it as well.
And if you're feeling extra generous,
feel free to write up a little read me.
Those do help people.
Do read them, I promise.
So if you feel like putting that in there,
if you don't have that sort of metadata
information inside of the works itself,
read me is never a bad thing to have.
All right.
So that's what I have right now.
And I will pass it back on over to Dean.
Yeah.
So thank you.
Greg, I want to say, you know, I,
I was part of the trace online
writing center for, for,
I guess from 2003 to a time.
It closed for just three years.
But I followed it online for many years
while it was developing.
And when they closed it down,
we took over the files from the server
from Nottingham Trent University
and from Sue Thomas and other people.
We ended up with 6129 files for Trace
Online Writing center, and I forgot
how the total number of index files
Greg helped me remember,
but something like 329 index files.
So each project had an index file.
And so if you want to find the index
index file,
that's hard too, because there were
three different versions of the website,
all kind of embodied into the same stuff.
So we're trying to recreate that community
in the lab for the for the next.
Right.
And to build out that community again.
And, but kind of sussing through that huge
bit of file and trying to figure out
which is the index file
for the most recent website,
because there's something like 1900 falls
associated with that.
It's a real world bugaboo.
So if you are developing things
and you want it to survive
and you want people to read it,
just keep in mind it helps to organize it
in a way that makes them sense.
I know your papers, you might just have
a folder of your throwing things.
Okay, fine, do that, but hold on to things
and if you have time
when you're retired, Dina,
as you said, you retired,
go through those materials
and help us figure out.
Do you really want to keep
that piece of paper?
You know,
know that I do look at everything.
So when I have web, when I have emails
in which you're cursing out somebody,
I do have that too.
I just won't put that online.
I'm saying you,
Dina, but there are some examples of that.
All right.
I'm going to turn this over now
to Ruth for metadata.
Hello, I'm
Ruth Woodcock, and I'm responsible
for updating the metadata for the works.
In the next,
I'm going to share my screen with you
and show you.
There
we go. So.
I'm navigating
from the should click on Elms.
Come on.
Work.
Okay I don't know
why it's not cooperating.
Re Re refresh
okay.
All right I'll try that.
Oh there it is now it's there okay, good.
So we share.
Yes, ma'am.
And click share
I'm not used to sharing my screen.
Sorry about that. Okay. Here we go.
All right.
We use the Elms extended
electronic metadata
schema as the framework for collecting
and providing data about works.
In the next, we actually developed
and extended Elms for mods,
which is used primarily for libraries.
There's a link for Elms on the notes
for this workshop.
Now you can see a description
of each element by clicking on the up
arrow to the right of the title.
Now there's a lot of lot of stuff here,
so I'm in the interest of.
So here if I click on this
you can see it gives you a little,
little description.
In the interest of time I'm just going to
briefly summarize each category.
So for work information
that refers to the work itself
based on the title, the ID is something
you don't need to worry about. It's
something that's generated automatically
when we add a work to the next
for work description.
If a work contains a description
on, say, a landing page, we use that
for the description
and if need be, we write
the description ourselves.
For version information.
This refers to the code of the work.
We had information about publishing
and copyright
technical aspects of the work,
such as programing, languages
and experiential aspects of the work
such as
and sensory modalities.
And I'm going to show you
an example at the end
so that you can see what those are,
the images or images we collect ourselves.
But you can see all this data here.
Whoops. Oh.
Oh, right.
Version accessibility information.
Dini and Richard Snyder developed
Elms 3.0 to address accessibility
considerations for visitors
with sensory sensitivities
during a retreat
hosted by triangle ASI at Duke University.
We at the lab
received a grant from the Society
of American Archivists
to apply these additional metadata fields
to a select
number of works
in the next as a proof of concept.
In a future grant project,
we'll be adding accessibility
metadata to all of the works in the next.
So you can see
we're looking at visual impact,
touch and sound, movement, gesture
copy information
refers to the actual physical or digital
copy of the work that we have.
So we may have one copy
of the same version of a work,
usually in different collections,
but not always.
This is where we record the actual
URL of the work in the next, and
we record the availability of the work,
its original location and provenance.
So you can see these elements here.
Entity information.
This refers to individuals or groups
who created, funded or published works.
Collection information.
This may be a collection of one author's
works,
or a collection of works
by a variety of authors.
And these fields that you see
here are internal fields for the next,
and we supply the metadata
for these fields.
Works.
External link information.
These are.
If a work is located
elsewhere on the next,
such as the author's website,
we add the URL to the work.
So for example
you Holly showed you Eric Lawyers
website
with with information about his works.
I'll add a link to
to his website
with his information about the work
as an external link.
But since the URL is outside of our own
archive on the next, it's
considered an external link.
Global information.
These are miscellaneous notes
that attach to either images
like alt text for for readers
or to work themselves.
So maybe just like an additional
miscellaneous note.
So let's look at a couple of examples.
The first one I'd like to show you
is Patchwork Girl.
And so the version information
you can see in the sidebar on the right.
This is how it looks as it goes in.
We've got the description of the work
underneath the images.
We've got a GIF or a couple of gifts
and maybe some still shots,
information about
all kinds of information.
This one is nice because there's three.
We have three different copies
in three different collections
David Cole, Marjorie Lewis
and Robert Swigert.
The next one I'd like to show
you, is an example of work
with the accessibility,
additional accessibility,
metadata.
And for that one,
we're going to look at Aleph Null.
This is one of my favorite works.
So you can see
like like Patchwork
Girl, we've got the title image,
but now we have a new paragraph
called Experiencing the Work.
This one describes
what a visitor would experience when they,
as they interact with the work.
And then on the right, you've
got some additional elements here content
timing, text format, color
and contrast,
touch and movement and gesture.
So those those elements are all added.
And you can see my related link at Jim
Andrew's site at vivo. Com.
And turn things back over to
thank you, Ruth.
And I want to say that I want to recognize
Richard Schneider, who's here
today in a car with his kids.
Richard and Richard painstakingly
worked on this, this accessibility.
When we were away.
It was a week at Duke.
Kind of had some time.
Erica Fulop was with us,
and we worked with disability specialists
who guided us through this process.
And we were so happy to get this,
get this funded by the SA.
So it was wonderful.
So Mellon Foundation
funded the triangle event
and then SA funded
the actual implementation of it.
I also want to echo what Holly says.
We love it when people start to notice
the pattern of collection.
So we it's real fun
for someone to come in and say, oh,
there's five different copies
of this work in the next,
and they're all in different collections.
It starts to show a pattern of people
sharing their work
among among each other,
or just the popularity of a work.
It says a lot about the reception
of a work, and we're trying to document
that in the next.
It's part of part of what we're doing.
I want to turn this over
now to one more thing I was going to
mention is about metadata.
Metadata is so important
because it tells the story of your work
without the work without you being there.
And if you do a good job with it,
someone can read the metadata
and get a good sense of what it is
and how it's supposed to function.
So if you want to
look at our metadata schema, if you need
extra help understanding what we're
trying to do, know that we're here
to help you guide you with that.
So Greg's going to talk about web
standards,
library Congress standards and all kinds
of information about software.
Greg. Absolutely.
And I'm going to first drop
this into the chat.
This is what we're going to be
taking a look at here,
as you're looking at making sure that your
your work, your project,
whatever it is that you're attempting to
preserve, is going to be future proof.
You might be wondering,
okay, what format should I use for things?
Right.
That's always that's always a question
that comes up because
there are so many different formats,
so many different things out there.
As you're as you're working
on, your project
can make your head spin, right?
And they change all the time. It seems to.
But luckily we have things
we have resources and places like, say,
with the Library of Congress
that has right here what is a recommended
formats statement,
where it has an entire page here
that's dedicated to if you're doing
textual works or still image
works all the way down to design
in 3D or web archives and email like,
what are the best format recommendations
for the preservation of these things?
So if I were to say pop into moving
image works and specifically
like digital and physical media
right in here, I could see like, oh, okay,
if I'm working with this physical media
that I've got right,
or this digital media that I've got right
here, DCP is probably a really good one.
Okay, fantastic.
And it's tiling me like exactly
what specifications would be best for it.
They have a column for both preferred,
which is the one that you would
definitely want to go for,
but also acceptable ones here.
So a ProRes QuickTime move
container would be fantastic for that.
Underneath file based and physical media,
you can see that an IMF file
or say the ProRes QuickTime file,
if you're working with just digital media
MPEG two is pretty fantastic.
You'll notice that acceptable.
It's like an MP for okay,
well that's still works but not the best.
And we'll see something similar.
If we were to go to audio works,
you can see that they're saying like
high resolution HRA files or wave based
files.
Acceptable will be things like PCM wave
or lossless
compression schemes or things like that.
You'll notice that nowhere in here
do they mention MP
three and four over in the video
section is acceptable, not preferred.
And you might think because again,
I'm speaking about web here,
but you might think, well, why?
Why is that not the case everybody uses
it's kind of a web standard.
Same with MP for
those are kind of the web standards.
One thing that you will find,
as you were looking at
what are considered to be the best
archival formats for these files,
is that what's best for archiving
isn't always what's best for production.
What we generally receive here in the lab
is production files, right?
That's what we that's what we get files
that are specifically created for, like,
you know, accessibility or streaming
on the web or something like that.
Right.
It's not as often that we get
we kind of celebrate
whenever we get
like an actual project file or the fully
uncompressed copies of those files
alongside an actual production copy.
Right.
So you'll see these, these differences
because uncompressed file formats,
meaning that it's the there's
no form of compression and it is the best
possible quality that you can get
are always the route that you want to go.
Right.
These formats might change over time.
The ones that are considered
to be accessible, or the best use case
online for streaming
and for things like that, that may change.
So might the preferred versions.
But the general rule of thumb
is that you always want to keep
some form of uncompressed file formats,
keep your projects,
keep all of that stuff.
It helps with the documentation.
It helps with archiving your process
as well as for any sort
of like intellectual property property,
right claims, those sorts of things,
like always keep those things on hand.
But of course, because you want to be
sharing this with people
around the world or,
you know, wherever you're planning on
actually releasing it,
you also want to have a production copy,
but I just want to make sure
that it's emphasized.
That is not the only copy you keep right.
Always back up those those uncompressed
file formats always
keep your project files whenever you can,
even if you can't access them.
If you're making like in Premiere Pro
and you know it's been ten years, well,
you probably can't access it
with the latest version
of the subscription model
that Adobe wants you to use,
but that doesn't mean
that it's completely gone.
It can be accessed with a earlier version
that we have.
So always keep your project files,
always keep uncompressed formats.
Take a look at these sorts of resources
online.
Find out what those best formats are.
Do that alongside the actual production
that you publish,
whether online or locally or whatever.
That's what I really want to emphasize
as the takeaway for for this section,
but I'm going to pass it on over to Deanie
so that she can continue
on in the presentation.
All right.
So we're
getting close to running out of time.
So I'm going to move kind of quickly
to the last bit of this stuff.
So if you want to stick around
a little longer
for questions and answers
we're going to be here very quickly.
We put together inventories.
If you turn over materials to us,
we go through
and make a list of everything
you've given us.
Usually give that back to the artist
to make sure that we didn't miss anything.
And then we generate a finding aid.
So let me show you quickly
what that looks like.
So let me do a screen share.
And what you're looking at here
is the one for Houlton.
Move this out of my way.
Zoom is always in the way.
I'll make this a bit bigger.
So you can see here
this is the finding aid.
You can see that it has
how many kind of sections.
We have a live in sections.
These are the finding aids
for everything from the physical
to some of the digital files.
And I have the box here next to me
of one of the boxes of Richard's.
And it's got the materials in here.
Box one.
Notice here, if you look down
here's everything in box one.
And so when Richard called me
and said he wanted a copy of his contract
with Eastgate Systems Inc., I just had to
go to the finding aid, find it,
and then go into the box and pull it out.
So the boxes are key to the finding aid.
It takes a bit of time
to do the finding aid and but
but this is what it looks like.
And so that's, that's basically
what what we do here in the lab.
And it's important that we do this.
We also have the digital files backed up.
And we'll be talking about that quickly
in terms of repositories and storage.
Where do you keep this material?
I'm going to go away from screen
Share now and talk to you directly.
So there's a brick and mortar.
There's lots of places
to turn your material over to.
Right.
So you can go to the Rubenstein
Rare Book and Manuscript.
They have three collections there
Judy Malloy, Stephanie Strickland,
and Rob Kendall.
The Ransom Library in Austin
has Michael Joyce.
Judy Malloy's work is also held at MoMA,
and there's some works on the shelf
at Stanford.
Stanford also holds the Bob Stein Voyager
Collection.
The next holds 48 collections of works.
So we're the largest collection
of electronic literature,
and we hold both the digital
and the physical.
Know that when you donate or you give
or you sell your material
to an organization,
they will take the physical media
that you've produced floppy disk CD-ROMs,
and they'll put it in a vault.
And it's probably not going to be
available to you to go back and look at.
They lock it up for long term
accessibility.
They also don't have access to computers
for you to go
and look at at the Rubenstein,
you can bring your own laptop
and they will let you use
look at some of the material,
but a lot of the material is locked up.
So be very careful
when you start to talk to people
about donating or selling your material.
I'm going to
then talk very quickly
about storage materials.
So what you're looking at here
is a special box that we buy.
So it takes money to do archival work.
And in this box I had the collection
of the ice bound continuum.
And some of you might remember
Aaron Reed and Jacob Garvey's
beautiful mobile app piece.
It came with a lot of physical media.
So if you're going to produce
digital work, produce some physical media
to go with it because it helps
to align the work with the time period
and give us some more material
to think about and use.
But it came with a book.
We have also the
the card that went with the Kickstarter,
and it also came with posters for the AR
part of the mobile apps.
You told your mobile app, get to
the poster and pull up part of the story,
and we have all the posters for that.
All of these sit in this very special box.
Know that even the plastic is plastic.
These are not from baggies or blad bags.
Even the file files that we're using
are special archival files
and the paper clips.
So everything we're using and everything
you want to use need to be in that,
in that kind of condition, because things
will yellow and deteriorate.
The company that we use
is called University Products.
Really simple.
And then finally Greg is going to touch
on digital storage solutions
like what do you need to use
for your long term preservation?
Greg, you want to talk about that
and then we'll we need to close up.
I would love to. Yeah,
we're running very short on time.
So I'm going to kind of speed
through this.
There's any one of these sections
could be its own talk
or having a lot in here,
but I just want to preface
this last section
by saying that the phrase
digital is forever
is completely misleading in my opinion.
I'm sure you all know this already,
but the next is proof of that, right?
We're all fighting against atrophy here,
and these digital items are beholden to
their physical components.
That's just kind of how it is.
So when it comes to storage solution,
the most important thing
is to back up your data
in more than one place.
I cannot stress that enough,
whether it's online or locally
or on an external drive, doesn't matter.
Back up your data
in more than one place. Two is good.
Even more is even better though.
Like back it up as many places as you can.
For many people,
that's probably going to mean
like mirroring external drives, right?
That's kind of the one of the ways
to go about doing it.
I think a lot of people do.
So if that's your route,
what I want to recommend
is that you definitely go with hard disk
drives over solid state drives.
SSDs are faster and better for daily work
because of that,
but HDDs are superior for long
term storage
if you use them correctly, because,
I mean, they're hard disk drives, right?
They've got a magnetic platter in there.
So they use that platter to store the data
rather than electrical
electrical charges.
Excuse me to store that data.
SSDs need to be periodically charged
to avoid data loss.
So I highly recommend just grabbing an HD.
Put in all your files on there
and then setting it away.
You know, like
don't don't chuck it obviously, but don't,
you know, don't access it regularly.
Don't overwrite that data.
Just put it in cold storage.
Just leave it be.
SSDs are fantastic for their speed
and they're very stable, but HDD
better for long term.
There are also long term
archival cloud storage services like,
I don't know,
Amazon, Glacier or Backblaze or
things like that
that are not like typical web hosting.
They're cloud
based services which are specifically
designed for long term storage.
You put your files in and you don't
access them for a long, long time.
And when you do want to access them,
you have to request access.
And then you get a little bit of a charge
for like the download.
But those are also fantastic services.
We use a more web
like a standard web service for the next,
because we want people to actually be able
to view those works through a browser.
So that can also be appealing to people.
But whatever you route, you go.
I really, really just want to emphasize
back it up in multiple places.
Always do that no matter what.
Multiple places one, two, three, four.
As many as you can get.
Yes. So I see we're hitting time
a little bit over.
So I'm going to pass it
back over to Dean for closing okay.
So that's a workshop in an hour.
Everything you want to know
about digital preservation.
If you have questions
I don't know if we have any time.
Do we have a minute for questions, Emily.
At all?
I can leave it
I yeah, I'll give you a minute
and then they'll yell at me for the video
if I don't close it soon.
So go ahead.
Question. Does anyone have questions?
Yes. Well very practical.
Thank you. Great. Great presentation.
What is your feeling about jQuery?
Jake?
Does jQuery.
Is that going to last or do you feel like.
And then if you change everything
the JavaScript, will that be refactoring?
I mean, will it be a reconstruction or.
I'm just curious
on that practical question.
I think that would be a restoration work,
I loved it.
Yeah, I agree with with Dini about,
you know, the minute
you completely rewrite the code,
I think a great example of this is,
is Dena Larsen's kanji, cuz
those were originally created
with Java applets which did deprecate.
And then we rewrote that in JavaScript.
But the way we rewrote that JavaScript
was completely different,
even conceptually code wise,
from how the athletes were coded.
And so that would absolutely be
a completely different reconstruction,
because the structure is such an important
part of these digital works.
So yes, we would save a jQuery work
if we needed to in the future, you know,
by rewriting or refactoring that code.
But it would be considered,
at least in our mind,
a reconstruction because of how
it is affecting the structure
and the underlying framework of what
that that artwork is.
And some are especially important to that.
You know,
I think about like Tarraco Gorge, right,
where a lot of that code
is actually part of the work itself too.
So if we change that code,
we're really changing,
you know, the heart
and the soul of the work too.
So yet another reason why
that would be considered a reconstruction.
Greg, your thoughts on jQuery longevity?
Absolutely.
I mean, anytime that you add another layer
to your project,
like you could write something
in JavaScript today that in 20 years
won't work, even though JavaScript
will more than likely be around, right?
JavaScript is very stable
because it's built into these browsers
is widely supported.
But the moment that you add
another layer, jQuery is maintained.
It's got a very active community.
Still, all these years later.
It's shocking,
but that could go down one year from now,
and then you're just kind of coasting
on that, that,
that production that somebody has created
and hoping that
it adheres to later
JavaScript changes, right.
Something might deprecate in JavaScript
that will break
the latest version of jQuery.
If it's not being maintained anymore,
you're dead in the water, right? So
as far as longevity is concerned,
it's hard to tell when communities
will stop being interested
in continuing to contribute
to an open source project like that.
You kind of have to watch those trends
and just kind of
get a feel for the community.
But if we're talking about preserving,
like creating future proof works,
the more that you can cut out
of your project that you have to rely on,
whether it be repositories or platforms
or services or applications,
whatever you can cut out
that will be more future proof.
But again, with the creative process,
you should use whatever you want.
So it's kind of a back and forth there
if you want it to be future proof.
So if her future, I mean,
it makes it makes sense to to go back to
those old works and even older JavaScript
and get that up more up to date.
Absolutely. Yeah. Okay.
But keep the versions that you had
initially, I guess.
Yeah. Yes. Keep those old versions too.
But you're just comment out the.
All that
being said, the next does use jQuery.
So you know, even even with everything
that Greg said, you know,
we do find it fairly stable at the moment
and feel comfortable using it in certain
places, even in our lives.
So yes, the problem we're trying to solve
now is how to save AI works.
And so a lot of the lot of the processes
we use for hypertext with the multiple
paths will be probably the direction we go
for AI narratives and things like that.
So we're already
putting our brains into that.
We're also working on saving VR.
Like how do we save VR works?
So there's a lot of work
that that needs to be done.
And we're trying to stay
at the forefront of this.
That's all the time we have.
And so thank you
so much, Bobby. You said thank you.
I'm glad you enjoyed that.
And we're happy to to talk to you
individually, anybody that's interested.
And we are here.
And thanks for giving us a couple
extra minutes to answer questions.
No worries.
It's okay. It's okay.
I'm going to close it now.
See you all in the chat or tomorrow
or wherever we're going next.
There's a performance
this evening as well.
All right. Thanks. Take care. All y'all.